Guide to the Labaree Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Labaree family papers
1801-1954
MS 596
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The principal figures in these papers are Benjamin Labaree and his wife, Eliza Paul Capen Labaree. Their papers consist of courtship letters and other correspondence (1831-1835), his autobiography written in 1879 and five of her school notebooks compiled while she was at the Ipswich Academy (ca. 1829-1830). Also in the papers is a sketchbook by James McIntosh, and a collection of family letters (1917-1919) edited by Leonard Woods Labaree and abridged by Rachel Capen Schauffler.
Labaree family
Scope and Contents
The Labaree Family papers bring together items pertaining to two generations of the Labaree family and the related Schauffler family. The older generation is represented by Benjamin Labaree (1801-1883) and his wife, Eliza Paul Capen (1804?-1835). Preserved here are twenty-four letters (1831-1835) exchanged between them during their courtship and short marriage, containing serious discussions of religion and marriage, and three letters to Eliza's mother, the second of which gives an account of Eliza's death. Benjamin Labaree's unpublished autobiography covers the same period of time and fleshes out the story of their experiences as missionaries and teachers on the Tennessee frontier. He also describes his earlier life as a teacher in North Carolina in the 1820s and his study at Dartmouth College and Andover Theological Seminary. Both the letters and the autobiography reveal a continuing interest in the lives and customs of the people among whom he lived, and particularly in the effects of slavery on both blacks and whites. Labaree also incorporates into his autobiography some family history, recounting the capture by Indians of his grandfather in the 1740s.
Five school notebooks of Eliza P. Capen are included in the collection; these were presumably compiled while she was a teacher at Miss Gilpah Grant's Ipswich Academy, ca. 1829-1830. With these is a transcript of her notes on pedagogy, reprinted in The New England Quarterly for September 1947.
The Labaree-Schauffler family is represented by Benjamin Labaree's great-grandson, Leonard Woods Labaree, a typescript of whose abridgment of "The Christian Fiend" by Rachel Capen Schauffler is included here. This work consists of transcripts of letters to and from Schauffler and Labaree family members and others during World War I. Labaree in his introduction speaks of it as a "common record... of the general experience and a cross-section of the military service...." Included are letters from men in training camps and at the front and from nurses and other women serving overseas.
Other items in the Labaree Family papers are a sermon by Dr. Codman and a sketchbook of James McIntosh, both presumably possessions of Eliza or Benjamin Labaree, and several newspaper clippingsaboutthe Schauffler family. Typed manuscripts of Benjamin Labaree and the correspondence have been made.
These papers were given to Yale University by Leonard Woods Labaree in 1939 and 1948.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Labaree-Schauffler family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Courtship; Death; Education; Families; Women -- Education; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States; Southern States; Autobiographies; Labaree, Benjamin, 1801-1883; Labaree, Eliza Paul Capen, 1804?-1835; Labaree, Leonard Woods, 1897-1980; Schauffler, Rachel Capen, b.1876; Labaree family
- Inventory
  - Labaree, Benjamin (1801-1883) and Eliza (Capen) Labaree (1804?-1835): correspondence
    - Originals, 1831-1835, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Typed transcripts (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Labaree, Benjamin (1801-1883): autobiography
    - Original, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Typed transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Labaree, Eliza Paul (Capen) (1804?-1835)
    - 5 school workbooks, [ca. 1829-1839] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Zilpah Grant and the Art of Teaching: 1829, As Recorded by Eliza Paul Capen," reprinted from The New England Quarterly, Vol. 20, 1947 September
  - [Codman, Dr. ?]: sermon, 1830 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - McIntosh, James: sketchbook, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Schauffler, Rachel Capen, ed.: "The Christian Fiend: Being the War-Time Correspondence of the Schauffler Family, 1917-1919"; abridged by Leonard Woods Larabee, undated (Box 2, Folder 8 - 11)
  - Schauffler family: newspaper clippings, 1940, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)